Finding Aid for Frank J. Cianciola papers, 1946-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank J. Cianciola papers
1946-2007
1972-1998
Cianciola, Frank J.
2008136 Aa2
Frank Cianciola was the Director of the Michigan Union system and played a major role in student programming and activities at the University of Michigan from 1980 to his retirement in 2007. Papers consist of correspondence, planning material, financial and budgetary records, and material produced by students at the University of Michigan, the majority of which span 1972-1998. The bulk of the collection represents Cianciola's role as Union administrator, which includes financial records and planning materials from major building renovations, and his work with the student population. The collection contains records created by Cianciola and Union administrators preceding him.
17.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in one accession (Donor No. 9856 ), February 2007.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
After receiving a B.A. in education from the University of Akron, Frank Cianciola began his career in student services by opening the Kent State University Student Center in 1973. He received his M.A in educational administration in 1978, also from the University of Akron, and moved to the University of Michigan as Director of the Michigan Union and Student Programs two years later. As director, Cianciola oversaw great changes in the Union, including the expansion and renovation of the Union building and the creation of programs intended to once again make the union a center for student life on campus.
During his tenure at Michigan, Cianciola's responsibilities expanded to include a close relationship with the student body. In 1992, he became the Associate Dean of Students. In 1999, Cianciola was named the interim Associate Vice President for Student Affairs and Dean of Students, transitioning to Senior Associate Vice President for Student Affairs in 2001, a position he held until his retirement in 2007. Through these positions, Cianciola played a major role in creating programs and policy for students and student organizations. As the liaison between student groups and the university administration, Cianciola was at the center of several controversies and major campus issues during his tenure, and had a close relationship with the Michigan Student Assembly, the University Activities Center, the University Cellar, and other student groups.
The Frank Cianciola Papers measure 17.5 linear feet and range from 1946 to 2007. The bulk of the material, however, dates from 1974 to 1998. The papers are divided into four series: Correspondence; Student Services Files; Topical Files; and Union System Administration Files.
Subjects:
Student unions--Management.; Michigan Union.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Student Affairs.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Student Services.; University of Michigan--Student life and customs--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Student life and customs--1981-1990.; University of Michigan--Student life and customs--1991-2000.; University of Michigan--Student life and customs--2001-2010.; Monroe Trotter House University of Michigan.; Hash Bash (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Michigan Student Assembly.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, 1978-2004 (1.25 linear feet) is comprised of letters and memos that cover a wide rage of topics. This series uses the basic original structure of Cianciola's filing system, with some files categorized by topic and others files from the 1980s organized chronologically. This series includes communication with University of Michigan administrators and correspondence centered on specific student activities and programming. The other series in this collection also contain correspondence that relate to their subject matter.
  - Associate Directors Meetings, 1982-1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Associate Dean for Special Services, 1993-1998 (Box 1)
  - Associate Dean of Students, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Associate Dean of Students, "Same Page" Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1980-1986
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Class Day Correspondence, 1994-1996
    - 1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Dean of Students, 1993-2005; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Governance Change, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Homecoming, 1993-1998 (Box 2)
  - Intergroup Relations, 2002-2004 (Box 2)
- Student Services Files
  The Student Services Files, 1972-2006 (7 linear feet) series is divided into three subseries: Minority Student Services, 1971-2005 (.75 linear feet) Programming, 1974-2006 (3 linear feet) and Student Groups, 1972-2006 (3.25 linear feet). These records represent Cianciola's role in providing programs directed at the student population, facilitating the work of student groups, and setting university policy affecting student life. The Minority Student Services subseries includes records on the administration of the William Monroe Trotter Multicultural Center, as well as programs and studies focusing on campus diversity and the university's relationship with minority students. The Programming subseries includes records from Student Organizations and Programs (SOAP), which developed student leadership and organizations; and the Office of Major Events, which staged large-scale concerts and shows for the general public. The Student Groups subseries represents Cianciola's work with student organizations, interest groups, and social policy. This subseries includes material from the Michigan Student Assembly, records concerning "Hash Bash" and the National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws, material documenting the sometimes contentious relationship between the administration and the student-managed University Cellar bookstore, and records surrounding the re-drafting of the controversial social events policy.
  - Minority Student Services
    - Administrative, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Pow Wow, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Budget, 1979-1986 (Box 2)
    - Candidate Process, 1981-1986 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1984; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Proposals, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - Ethnic Theater Festival, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic Students, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs (MESA) Correspondence, 1997-2005; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs (MESA)/Student Activities and Leadership (SAL)/Intergroup Relations (IGR) Work, circa 1998; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Report: 1993 Survey of Students, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Staff Meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Trotter House, Financial, 1983-1988 (Box 2)
    - Trotter House, General, 1972-1988 (Box 2)
    - Trotter House, Selection Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Programming
    - Artists and Craftsman Guild, 1980-1984; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Asian American Awareness Events Report, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Co-Curricular Programs, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Co-Curricular Programs: Programs Review, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Committee for the Graduation
      - General, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
      - General, 1993-1998 (Box 3)
      - Memos, 1982-1984 (Box 3)
      - Memos, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
      - Memos, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
      - Planning, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Committee for the Graduation, Recommendations for the Future, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Community Service and Learning, Planning, 1996-2000 (Box 3)
    - Community Service and Learning, Printed Material, 1993-2006; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Counseling and Psychological Services, Correspondence, 1988-2001 (Box 3)
    - Counseling and Psychological Services, General, 2001-2006; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Dean of Students Annual Report, 1994/95 (Box 4)
    - Disabled Student Services, 1993-2005; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Diversity Days Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - Diversity Subcommittee, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Eclipse Jazz, General, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Eclipse Jazz, Grant Applications, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Festifall, 1981; 1984 (Box 4)
    - Film Groups, 1974-1980 (Box 4)
    - Freshman Convocation
      - 1987-1988 (Box 4)
      - 1989 (Box 4)
      - 1990 (Box 4)
      - 1991 (Box 4)
    - Gender Identity Work Group, 2002-2003 (Box 4)
    - Latino Programs, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Major Events Office
      - Correspondence, 1986; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - General
        - 1981 (Box 4)
        - 1982 (Box 4)
        - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - Promoter Agreements, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Martin Luther King JR, Day, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Leadership Initiatives, General, 1997-1998; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Michigan Leadership Initiatives, Learning Leadership Reports, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Madness, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - Peace Corps 20th Anniversary, 1980 (Box 5)
    - A Profile of Selected Student Affairs, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Programming (cont.) (Box 5)
    - Project Community Class Schedules, circa 1989 (Box 5)
    - Promotional Fliers from Union, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Report of Experiential and Developmental Programming, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Shades of the U Correspondence, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Student Organizations and Programs (SOAP)
      - Administrative Staff Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence and Planning, 1978-1983; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Handouts, undated (Box 5)
      - Needs Assessment, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Publications, circa 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Student Affairs Statement, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Student Organization Development Center
      - Annual Report (Box 5)
      - General, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Student Organizations and Programs Evaluations, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Student Pledge Program, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Union Programming Committee, 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Union Recreation, 1978-1985 (Box 6)
  - Student Groups
    - Commission on Student Governance
      - Interim Report, 1974 (Box 6)
      - Report, 1974 (Box 6)
      - Report, Second Printing, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Committee on the Underclass Experience Report (Box 6)
    - Dance Marathon, 1999-2005 (Box 6)
    - Dance Party Policy, 1997 (Box 6)
    - Dance Party Policy Open Forum Audio Cassettes, 1997 (Box 6)
    - Dance Party Review, 1997 (Box 6)
    - Drug Study, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Hash Bash and National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws (NORML)
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 6)
      - 1993 (Box 6)
      - 1994 (Box 6)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 6)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 6)
      - 2000-2001, 2005 (Box 6)
      - Meetings, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Student Assembly (MSA)
      - Commission to Study Student Governance Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      - Constitution/Registration Information, 1983-1993 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence (Box 7)
        - 1979 (Box 7)
        - 1995-1996 (Box 7)
        - 1996-2005, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - General, 1989-1998; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Preliminary Review, circa 1991 (Box 7)
      - Report on South University Tear-gassing Incident, 1991 (Box 7)
      - Student Fee Assessment Request, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Student Fee Project, 1997-2004 (Box 7)
      - Student Fee Request, 2006 (Box 7)
      - Tax Issue (Box 7)
      - Year End Report, 2002 (Box 7)
    - Publicity Handbook for Student Organizations, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Social Events Alcohol Policy, 1991-2000; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Social Events Policy, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Social Events Policy, 1995-1997; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Student Government Council Legislation, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Student Life Survey
      - 1999-2000 (Box 8)
      - 2000-2005 (Box 8)
    - Student M-Quality Project, 1994; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Student Recognition Awards, 1995-2003 (Box 8)
    - Student Wood and Craft Shop, 1981-1982 (Box 8)
    - University Cellar
      - Correspondence, 1976-1981; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Insurance and Safety, 1973-1978 (Box 8)
      - Lease Agreement, 1972-1975; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Lease Agreement, 1974-1981 (Box 8)
      - Space and Rental Calculations, 1972-1979 (Box 8)
    - University Activities Center (Box 9)
      - General, 1970-1979 (Box 9)
      - General, 1980-1983 (Box 9)
      - Merger, 1963-1989 (Box 9)
      - Report, 1973 (Box 9)
    - WCBN (Campus Broadcasting Network) Fundraiser, 1988 (Box 9)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files, 1974-2007 (2.75 linear feet) consists of material dealing with disparate subject matter, including the effects of alcohol on campus, Union fundraising material, and minority groups and issues.
  - Alcohol and Other Drugs
    - Binge Drinking Report, 1999 (Box 9)
    - General, 1991-2006; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - "A University Community Approach to Alcohol and Drugs" Report, 1991 (Box 9)
  - Americans with Disabilities Act
    - Correspondence, 1992; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - General, 1974-1989 (Box 9)
  - Americorps, 1999-2003 (Box 9)
  - The Arts Advisory Board, 1997-1998 (Box 9)
  - Associate Dean for Multiculturalism, 1993-2002 (Box 9)
  - Association of Religious Counselors, 2002-2007 (Box 10)
  - Athletics, 1997-2003 (Box 10)
  - Club Sports, 1999-2000 (Box 10)
  - Day One Project, 1995 (Box 10)
  - Fan Behavior, 2003 (Box 10)
  - Functional Review Counseling, circa 1982 (Box 10)
  - Fundraising, General, 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Fundraising, Phonathons, 1985-1987; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Fundraising Plan, 1984 (Box 10)
  - Hate Bias Reporting, 2005 (Box 10)
  - Hate Mail, 1994-1996 (Box 10)
  - Health Services, 1999-2000 (Box 10)
  - Intercultural Leadership Seminar, 1997-1999 (Box 10)
  - LeaderShape Conference, Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 10)
  - LeaderShape Conference, General, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Lesbian-Gay Male Program Office (LGMPO), 1992-2005; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Meningitis, 1999-2005 (Box 10)
  - Mental Health Service for Students Work Group, General, 2001-2005; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Mental Health Service for Students Work Group, Report, 2003 (Box 11)
  - Minority Students and Issues, circa 1970-1977 (Box 11)
  - Minority Students and Issues, 1986-1992; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Minority Students and Issues, "The Black Student Lounge,", 1989 (Box 11)
  - Office of Religious Affairs Proposal, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Rose Bowl Tour, 1997-1998 (Box 11)
  - Senior Staff Meetings Notebook, 1997-1998 (Box 11)
  - Serve/Lean Grant, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Speaker Initiative, 1998-1999 (Box 11)
  - University Health Service Fee Options, 1999-2000 (Box 11)
  - University Task Force on Community Service Learning, 1993-1994; 4 folders (Box 11)
- Union System Administration Files
  The Union System Administration Files, 1946-2006 (6.5 linear feet) consists of four subseries: Facilities, 1956-2007 (3.25 linear feet) Financial, 1946-1991 (.75 linear feet) Franchises and Retail, 1971-1994 (.5 linear feet) and Planning and Reports, 1968-1999 (2 linear feet). These records represent the management of the university Union system, including facilities management and fiscal operations. This series contains a large portion of material created by union administrations prior to Cianciola's arrival in 1980. The Facilities subseries contains records pertaining to the physical assets of the Union system including the Michigan League, Union, and Pierpont Commons buildings, and the common areas of the university, including the Diag. Of note are records and construction plans from several major renovations of the Michigan Union, and the policy governing the use of the Diag. The Facility subseries is organized around each facility or area. The Financial subseries contain much of the older records in the collection. The Financial and the Planning and Reports subseries are organized chronologically.
  - Facilities
    - Diag and Open Areas
      - Common Areas Policy (Box 12)
        - Agendas and Minutes, 1994 (Box 12)
        - Review, 1994 (Box 12)
        - Current Information, 1994 (Box 12)
    - Diag and Open Areas
      - General, 1992-1993 (Box 12)
      - Outdoor Space Policy Revisions, 1993-1994 (Box 12)
      - Diag Policy Development
        - 1989-1992 (Box 12)
        - 1992-1994, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Michigan League
      - Building Survey and Planning Material, 1988-1991 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence
        - 1981-1991 (Box 12)
        - 1991-1993, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - General, circa 1978 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Union
      - General
        - Catering Policy, 1988 (Box 12)
        - Correspondence, 1969-1977; 2 folders (Box 12)
        - House Rules, 1974-1979; 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous Policies, 1987-2007; 3 folders (Box 13)
        - Piano Policy, 1982-1983 (Box 13)
        - Policy, 1956; 1960; 1967; 1969 (Box 13)
        - Scheduling Improvements for the Michigan Union, 1990 (Box 13)
        - Scheduling and Operations, Monthly Reports, 1995-2000; 4 folders (Box 13)
        - Scheduling Policy, 1976-1982; 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Scheduling Policy, 1983-1985 (Box 13)
        - Scheduling Policy, 1986 (Box 13)
        - Space Allotment, 1972-1979; 3 folders (Box 13)
        - Union History, ca. 1979-, circa 1988 (Box 13)
        - Works of Art in the Michigan Union, 1956-1979 (Box 13)
      - Renovations
        - Pre-1972 Renovations (Box 13)
        - Renovation, 1974/75
          - Construction Plans, 1973-1975; 3 folders (Box 13)
          - Construction Plans and Correspondence, 1974 (Box 14)
        - Renovation, 1981/82
          - Asbestos Problem, 1982 (Box 14)
          - Background Information, 1977-1981 (Box 14)
          - Bidding, Contracts, and Specifications, 1981 (Box 14)
          - Construction Plans and Shop Drawings, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 14)
          - General Planning and Notes, circa 1981 (Box 14)
          - Program Statement, 1981 (Box 14)
          - Renovation Interview, 1981 (Box 14)
          - Renovation Master Plan and Design Guidelines, 1981-1982 (Box 14)
        - Renovation Binder, 1995/96 (Box 14)
    - Pierpont (North Campus) Commons
      - General Planning, circa 1990 (Box 15)
      - Renovations, 1995-1997 (Box 15)
      - Strategic Facility Plan, Final Report, 2000 (Box 15)
      - Strategic Facility Plan, Interim Report, 1999 (Box 15)
  - Financial
    - Probate and Trust Funds, 1946-1952; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Examinations of Financial Statements
      - 1959, 1961 (Box 15)
      - 1962-1964 (Box 15)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 15)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 15)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 15)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 15)
    - Trust and Investments, 1972-1976; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Internal Audit of Financial Statements, 1976; 1978 (Box 15)
    - Budget, 1979/80 (Box 15)
    - Auxiliary Fund Summary, 1979/80-1984/85 (Box 15)
    - Financial Update, 1979/80-1984/85 (Box 15)
    - Square footage and Rental Costs, 1980-1982 (Box 15)
    - Budget, 1986 (Box 15)
    - Budget and General Financial, 1988-1991 (Box 15)
  - Franchises and Retail
    - Foodservice
      - Financial, 1992 (Box 16)
      - Food Service Action Plan, 1994 (Box 16)
      - Goals and Objectives, 1996 (Box 16)
      - Michigan Union Dinning Room Study, 1984 (Box 16)
      - Student Employee Manual, 1984 (Box 16)
      - University Club, 1974-1982; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - General
      - Franchises, 1971-1977 (Box 16)
      - North Campus Commons Caf Proposal (Espresso Royale), 1991 (Box 16)
      - Retail Operations, 1982-1984 (Box 16)
      - Union Mall Franchises, 1985-1987 (Box 16)
  - Planning and Reports
    - Operational Analysis of the University of Michigan Union, 1968 (Box 16)
    - Management by Objectives in Student Services, 1976 (Box 16)
    - Report on the Michigan Union (Sturgis Report), 1978 (Box 16)
    - Accountability Systems in the Office of Student Services, 1979 (Box 16)
    - Michigan Union Market Study, 1979 (Box 16)
    - Michigan Union Market Study, Data, 1979 (Box 16)
    - 1Report of the Task Force to Study the Future of the Michigan Union, 979 (Box 16)
    - Union Task Force, 1979 (Box 16)
    - University of Michigan Ann Arbor Self-Study Report, 1979/80 (Box 17)
    - Goals and Objectives, 1980 (Box 17)
    - Planning Process, 1985 (Box 17)
    - What is the Union, 1985 (Box 17)
    - Goals and Objectives, 1986 (Box 17)
    - Goals and Objectives, 1987; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Perceptions of the University Record, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Michigan Union Organizational Assessment, 1989 (Box 17)
    - Michigan Union Organizational Assessment, Correspondence, 1989 (Box 17)
    - Annual Report, 1989/90 (Box 17)
    - Co-Curricular Programs and Unions, Goals, 1994/95-1995/96 (Box 18)
    - Annual Report and Annual Objectives, 1994/95-1995/96 (Box 18)
    - Co-Curricular Programs and Unions, Goals and Action Plans, 1995 (Box 18)
    - Associate Vice-President, Dean of Students Annual Report, 1994/95 (Box 18)
    - Associate Vice-President, Dean of Students Annual Report, 1995/96 (Box 18)
    - Quarterly Reports, 1998-1999; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - University Union Portfolio General Planning, 1999; 2 folders (Box 18)